Welcome to the Huberman Lab Podcast,
where we discuss science
and science-based tools for everyday life.
I'm Andrew Huberman,
and I'm a professor of neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine.
Today we are discussing tools for mood and mental health.
I will include tools and resources
taken from the guest episode that I did
with Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett,
who is a psychologist and neuroscientist
whose laboratory focuses on mood and emotions.
During that episode, she mentioned several important tools
that I do believe everybody should apply
and that indeed I've been applying to my own life
and have found to be extremely beneficial.
I will also highlight
some of the specific research articles
those tools are based on,
which were not covered in the podcast with Lisa.
I will also discuss tools gleaned
from the four episode series that I did on mental health
with Dr. Paul Conti,
who is a medical doctor specializing in psychiatry.
And that episode, as some of you may already know,
focused on mental health and the self,
as well as relationships.
And it included a deep discussion of what is the self.
We talked about the unconscious mind and the conscious mind.
And we also covered a lot of tools
for understanding oneself,
both within the context of therapy,
but also within the context of things
that one can do alone and that require zero cost.
In addition, we talked about tools
for improving relationships.
We talked about first principles of self care.
So I will provide highlights and takeaways
of those tools during today's episode.
And thirdly, I will include tools,
what we often refer to as protocols,
gleaned from some recent publications.
Indeed, publications that came out
as recently as two weeks ago,
which really emphasize specific things that we can all do
that again are zero cost,
that have been shown in quality peer reviewed research
to significantly improve mood and mental health.
For instance, if you're a regular listener of this podcast,
you are probably familiar with my nearly constant reminder
that people should view morning sunlight
and afternoon sunlight.
And if you can't, to embrace some alternatives
like looking at bright artificial light,
although sunlight is best.
Well, there was a recent paper published
in the journal, Nature Mental Health, an excellent journal,
focusing on not just the positive effects
of viewing light at those times of day
and indeed throughout the day,
but also the independent and positive effects
of being in darkness for six to eight hours every night.
That's right.
Not only is light during the day correlated
with significantly improved mental health outcomes,
but darkness at night that is avoiding lights,
not just bright lights, but lights for up to eight hours
at certain periods of your 24 hour circadian cycle
has been correlated with improved mental health outcomes.
And indeed has been shown to significantly offset
certain negative mental health outcomes.
This is a spectacular study.
Again, it involved a enormous number of research subjects,
more than 85,000 research subjects.
And it touches on a large number of actionable protocols
that I've distilled down to just one or two things
that all of us can easily do to improve our mood
and mental health on a consistent basis.
Before we begin, I'd like to emphasize that this podcast
is separate from my teaching and research roles at Stanford.
It is however, part of my desire and effort
to bring zero cost to consumer information about science
and science related tools to the general public.
In keeping with that theme,
I'd like to thank the sponsors of today's podcast.
Our first sponsor is Plunge.
Plunge makes what I believe is the most versatile
at home self-cooling cold plunge
for deliberate cold exposure.
I've covered the topic of deliberate cold exposure
several times on this podcast.
Indeed, we did an entire episode
about deliberate cold exposure.
And what's very clear from the research literature
is that deliberate cold exposure
can induce dramatic positive shifts
in so-called catecholamines.
That is dopamine, norepinephrine and epinephrine.
This is a small collection of molecules
that are released in the brain and body
when we do deliberate cold exposure.
And that subjectively lead to greatly enhanced feelings
of mood alertness and focus for many hours afterwards.
That's perhaps the best substantiated reason
and the most popular reason
why people who get into deliberate cold exposure,
no pun intended,
continue to do deliberate cold exposure
on a consistent basis.
Plunge uses a powerful and very easy to use
cooling filtration and sanitation unit
to give you access to deliberate cold exposure
in clean water whenever you want.
I've used a Plunge for several years now,
and I really like it because first of all,
it can use a standard outlet.
You don't have to modify the electricity
in your home or yard, and it's very easy to clean.
In fact, it stays clean for long periods of time,
which makes it very easy to maintain as well.
Plunge has several different models
to select from, including their new all-in cold Plunge,
which offers faster cooling,
smartphone connectivity, and more.
If you're interested in getting a Plunge,
you can go to Plunge, spelled P-L-U-N-G-E.com slash Huberman
to get $150 off your cold Plunge.
Again, that's plunge.com slash Huberman to get $150 off.
Today's episode is also brought to us by 8 Sleep.
8 Sleep makes smart mattress covers with cooling,
heating, and sleep tracking capacity.
I've spoken many times before in this podcast
about the fact that sleep,
that is getting enough quality sleep on a consistent basis,
is the foundation of mental health,
physical health, and performance.
Now, one of the key things
to getting the best possible night's sleep
is to control the temperature of your sleeping environment,
and that's because in order to fall and stay deeply asleep,
your body temperature needs to drop
by about one to three degrees.
And in order to wake up feeling refreshed and energized,
your body temperature actually has to increase
by about one to three degrees.
With 8 Sleep, controlling the temperature
of your sleeping environment is made extremely easy.
8 Sleep mattress covers allow you to program
the temperature of your sleeping environment
at the beginning, middle, and end of your night.
It can even divide the temperature
on the two sides of the bed for different people.
It also has sleep tracking capacity.
It will tell you how much slow wave sleep
and rapid eye movement sleep you're getting,
and really help you dial in the exact parameters
so you can get the best possible night's sleep.
I've been sleeping on an 8 Sleep mattress cover
for well over two years now,
and it has significantly improved my sleep,
and therefore my daytime mood focus and alertness.
If you'd like to try 8 Sleep,
you can go to 8sleep.com slash Huberman
and save up to $150 off their pod three covers.
8 Sleep currently ships in the USA, Canada, UK,
select countries in the EU, and Australia.
Again, that's 8sleep.com slash Huberman.
Today's episode is also brought to us by Waking Up.
Waking Up is a meditation app
that includes hundreds of meditation programs,
mindfulness trainings, yoga nidra sessions,
and NSDR, non-sleep deep rest protocols.
I started using the Waking Up app a few years ago
because even though I've been doing regular meditation
since my teens, and I started doing yoga nidra
about a decade ago, my dad mentioned to me
that he had found an app,
turned out to be the Waking Up app,
which could teach you meditations of different durations
and that had a lot of different types of meditations
to place the brain and body into different states,
and that he liked it very much.
So I gave the Waking Up app a try,
and I too found it to be extremely useful
because sometimes I only have a few minutes to meditate,
other times I have longer to meditate,
and indeed I love the fact that I can explore
different types of meditation
to bring about different levels of understanding
about consciousness, but also to place my brain and body
into lots of different kinds of states
depending on which meditation I do.
I also love that the Waking Up app
has lots of different types of yoga nidra sessions.
For those of you who don't know,
yoga nidra is a process of lying very still,
but keeping an active mind.
It's very different than most meditations,
and there's excellent scientific data
to show that yoga nidra and something similar to it
called non-sleep deep rest or NSDR
can greatly restore levels of cognitive and physical energy
even with just a short 10 minute session.
If you'd like to try the Waking Up app,
you can go to wakingup.com slash Huberman
and access a free 30 day trial.
Again, that's wakingup.com slash Huberman
to access a free 30 day trial.
Okay, let's talk about tools
for improving mood and mental health.
I think it goes without saying
that these are extremely important topics
for everyone not just to know about,
but in my opinion, also for people to implement.
And the reason is that we are currently
in a worldwide mental health crisis.
And while we could debate the reason
why we are in a worldwide mental health crisis,
it's very, very clear that mood disorders
and challenges with mental health abound.
And of course, there are many different therapies
for the treatment of mood disorders and mental health,
everything from talk therapy with a psychologist
or a psychiatrist or social worker,
prescription drug treatments,
their nutritional approaches, somatic approaches.
And I want to be clear that I do believe
that there's value in all of these approaches.
What tends to matter in terms of what sorts of tools
and approaches one adopts includes both access,
so whether or not people have access
to these types of therapies,
whether or not they can afford them on a consistent basis,
and also, of course, the severity of the mood
or mental health disorder.
And I'd be remiss, of course,
if I didn't make the statement,
and I don't say this just to protect me,
I also say this to protect all of you
and those that you know,
that if you are concerned about yourself or somebody else
having a serious mood or mental health disorder,
please do seek out help from a licensed clinical psychologist
or psychiatrist or other healthcare professional
who's qualified to help you in that regard.
With that said, we can now have a discussion
about tools and protocols for enhancing mood
and mental health that truly apply to everybody,
regardless of age.
To start off, I wanna talk about a fundamental aspect
of mood and mental health enhancement
that was discussed both in the guest episode
with Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett,
as well as in the guest series with Dr. Paul Conti.
And that has to do with what Dr. Paul Conti referred to
as the first principles of self-care or mental health.
The first principles of self-care include,
but are not limited to,
taking excellent care of one's biology,
which of course includes both the mind and the body.
And in order to make this very simple and actionable,
I've distilled out what I refer to as the big six.
I've sometimes referred to these
as the six major pillars of health,
both mental health and physical health,
as well as performance for that matter.
But if we're going to talk about tools
for mood and mental health,
we absolutely can't discard discussions about our biology.
That is, we need to make sure that we're taking care
of our normal biological function
and indeed enhancing the production
of specific neurotransmitters and neuromodulators
that we are optimizing.
Yes, I use the word optimizing.
The function of our so-called autonomic nervous system,
that aspect of our nervous system
that's humming in the background all the time.
It's operating unconsciously
to regulate our sleep-wake cycles.
It's regulating how well or poorly we react to things.
It's regulating how much dopamine, serotonin,
epinephrine, acetylcholine we're producing.
All of this stuff is humming in the background
and sets the stage for all the conscious work
that we might put to, for instance,
trying to understand what our life narrative is,
what our unconscious mind is doing,
what sorts of defenses am I producing,
all of the sort of high-level and directed work
that we're going to talk about a little bit later
exists on a background of autonomic function,
of neurotransmitter production, of hormone production,
not just testosterone and estrogen,
but things like cortisol, prolactin and on and on.
So it's important to understand that if our goal
is to be in the best possible mood
given our life circumstances
and to have the best possible mental health
and to improve our mood and mental health
consistently over time,
that we have to pay attention to what I'm referring to here
as the big six or the six pillars of mental health.
And those are, just to list them off,
then I'll go into a little bit more detail,
sleep, sunlight, although I'd like to modify sunlight
because based on some new data
that just came out a couple of weeks ago,
I'd like to now make that second pillar,
not sunlight, but light slash dark.
So we could even just think about it as a light,
when and how much light you get.
But what you'll soon learn is that how much dark you get
is also extremely important.
So we've got sleep, light, movement is the third,
nutrition, social connection, and stress control.
Now, these are topics that I've spoken about extensively
on previous Huberman Lab Podcast episodes.
So I don't want to go into a deep dive
of each of these six pillars right now,
but I am going to just give you a few highlights of each.
And then of course, we will provide links
in the show note captions
for which you can go on the deep dive if you like.
And I also would like to mention that
if you ever have questions about specific protocols
or tools and you're seeking those out
to our previous episodes or specific timestamps
of previous episodes of this podcast,
you can go to our newly revamped hubermanlab.com website
and put any topic of interest
or even several topics of interest into the search function.
And it will take you to the very specific timestamps
and other resources that provide information on those topics.
So I'm going to go into a few of the key bullet points
about each of the six pillars,
or what I also refer to as the big six
of self-care and mental health.
Again, this is a necessary list, but is not sufficient.
Again, necessary to do these things every 24 hours,
indeed, every 24 hours,
if you want to have the best possible mood
and mental health, but it is not sufficient.
That means you still need to do some of the other things
that we're going to talk about
in terms of directed approaches
at improving mood and mental health.
If you are to quote unquote,
optimize your mood and mental health,
or if you are, let's just say,
trying to constantly improve your mood and mental health.
But these are the necessary,
but not sufficient pillars of mental health.
So under the heading of sleep,
it's safe to say that most people need
between six to eight hours of sleep per night.
Some people can get away with five.
Some people need as much as nine or 10.
Certainly growing kids, babies, teenagers,
and those that are suffering from some sort of illness
are going to need more, as much as nine, 10,
maybe even 12 hours of sleep per night.
However, most people do well to get somewhere
between six and eight hours of sleep per night.
You're just going to have to experiment
and figure out what's best for you.
Now, one thing I heard recently,
so I can't claim this as an original idea,
but that I think is a really good way to think about sleep,
is that sleep, much like physical fitness,
is something that we have to constantly be working on.
It's not the sort of thing
where you can get a great night's sleep one night,
and then the next night,
just kind of let all the protocols go
and expect to get a great night's sleep.
You don't have to be neurotic
about getting a great night's sleep.
Indeed, I do believe that we should strive
to get enough quality sleep
as many of the nights of our life as possible,
and if you can't do that, hopefully it's for good reasons,
but of course, things happen in life, raising kids,
you have emergencies, all-nighters to study,
so you can make sure you get that best possible grade
on an exam, et cetera, et cetera,
but we should all strive to get the best quality sleep
that we can, and as much of it, most nights of our lives.
So it's important to look at sleep as a process
that you're going to be working on
for the rest of your life, just like fitness,
and I don't say that to overwhelm you,
I say that so that if on any given night
you get a poor night's sleep,
you don't stress that too much,
you just get right back on the wagon
and you try and get the best possible night's sleep
the next night and the next night and the next night,
much like fitness.
There's no 10-week program
that's going to transform your physical fitness forever,
just like there's no sleep program
that's going to transform your sleep forever.
It's a daily or rather, I should say, nightly investment,
although some of the things
that are going to positively impact your sleep
or perhaps damage your sleep
are things that you do during the daytime, right?
So avoid that caffeine too late in the day,
get that morning sunlight and on and on,
but view sleep as something
that you're constantly investing in,
and it is a critical investment
for your mood and mental health.
The other thing that's not often discussed,
and I really haven't talked about terribly much
on this podcast, is the importance
of having a fairly consistent sleep routine.
Now, I realize that not everybody can get to sleep
at the exact same time each night
and wake up at the exact same time each morning,
and frankly, that's not practical.
I certainly don't do that.
However, what we know from the circadian health literature
is that everybody should strive,
again, that's strive, nobody's perfect,
but strive to get to sleep
at more or less the same time each night
and wake up at more or less the same time each morning.
This turns out to be really important
for regulating mood and mental health,
and indeed for improving your overall levels of sleep,
getting the optimal amounts of slow wave sleep,
aka deep sleep and rapid eye movement sleep.
And what we know is that ideally you're going to get
to sleep within plus or minus one hour
of your regular sleep time.
So if your regular two bed time is 10 o'clock,
you're used to getting in bed at 10 o'clock
and falling asleep somewhere around 10.30.
Well, then if the next night you fall asleep at 9.30, great.
You're still within the plus or minus one hour.
And if the next night you go to sleep
and you don't fall asleep till 11.30, don't sweat it.
In fact, you're still within that plus or minus one hour.
However, if you start getting into a habit
of going to bed at vastly different times,
deviating more than or less than one hour
from your normal to bed time,
well, then you're going to start to run into issues
such as waking up feeling groggy,
even if you got enough sleep.
So even if you slept the full eight hours
that you're used to getting,
people who go to sleep much later than they normally do
or much earlier than they normally do
start getting into kind of issues of mood regulation,
energy regulation, not just in the morning,
but in the afternoon.
Likewise, try and wake up at more or less the same time
each morning, plus or minus one hour.
That's really going to help you anchor
your overall sleep schedule.
And it's really going to help lead to predictability
of your overall levels of energy, mood
and focus throughout the day.
The second pillar in that big six is light.
And I used to refer to this as sunlight, right?
I'd say, and I'm going to say it again now,
although I've covered this in a lot more detail.
So again, just hitting the top contour critical elements,
try to view sunlight, that is with your eyes,
view sunlight as early as possible after waking.
Whenever I say that, the most common question I get is,
what do I do if I wake up before the sun comes out?
Well, unless you have superpowers that I'm not aware of,
you can't make the sun come out any earlier.
So just flip on artificial lights as needed
until the sun comes out and then get outside,
face east in the morning, take off those sunglasses.
It's perfectly safe to look at low solar angle sunlight
without sunglasses, providing you're not driving
into bright light and you crash, this kind of thing.
Get outside, look at the sunlight,
definitely blink to protect your eyes as needed,
but get that sunlight in your eyes early in the day.
This has myriad positive effects on mood focus
and alertness and nighttime sleep later that night.
And it does so through a number of well-defined biological
and endocrine hormonal pathways that I've discussed
on many previous podcast episodes.
And you want to do this for about 10 minutes
on non-overcast days and as long as 20 or 30 minutes
on overcast days.
And that highlights the second most common question I get,
which is, what do I do if there's no sun where I live?
I live in an area where there's no sunlight.
Look, if you live on planet earth, there's always sunlight.
There might not be very much of it.
That might be very overcast where you live.
It might seem very dark, but trust me,
there's far more photons, light energy coming
through that cloud cover,
even in the darkest mornings of winter,
than there are at night in those dark winters.
So get that light in your eyes
and do it as consistently as possible
and also do that in the late afternoon and evening.
That's critical for regulating your circadian clock
for reasons that I've talked about previously,
but I'll get into in a future podcast,
really explaining how those clock oscillators
and mechanisms work.
But just to keep it really simple,
since this is a toolkit episode
for mood and mental health,
your mood and your mental health will benefit tremendously
from getting morning sunlight in your eyes.
Now, if you need to get more light in your eyes,
because indeed there's just not enough sunlight
or you don't have the opportunity to get outside
and view sunlight in the morning for whatever reason,
you might invest in getting a bright light source
that you can plug in.
You probably want one that's as bright as 10,000 lux.
So that's pretty bright.
Those fall under the category of so-called SAD lamps,
seasonal effective disorder lamps.
And you can purchase those.
They can be somewhat expensive.
You can also opt to get a 900 lux drawing tablet.
By the way, I have no financial relationship
to any of these sorts of light sources,
but you can find them pretty easily.
And in the case of the 900 lux light tablet,
fairly inexpensively online.
And you can put that on your desk
or where you have your morning coffee
and try and enhance the total amount of light
that you're getting in the morning.
But frankly, nothing is as good as sunlight.
So if you can't get sunlight,
you might think about investing in one of those SAD lamps.
And indeed those SAD lamps aren't as good as sunlight,
but they are the next best thing
if you really can't get sunlight on a consistent basis.
A few other fine points that I always get asked about.
First of all, it is absolutely okay
to wear eyeglasses or contact lenses.
Those sorts of corrective lenses
are actually going to focus the light to your retina,
which is where you want it.
However, this whole process of viewing morning sunlight
in afternoon light does not, again,
does not work through a window or windshield
because windows and windshields
filter out the relevant wavelengths of light
that you want to get directly onto your retina.
Okay, so that's the reality of it.
In addition, please don't feel
that you have to look directly at the sun
and certainly don't stare at the sun.
Never force yourself to look at any light,
sunlight or otherwise,
that's so bright that it's painful to look at.
So if it's comfortable for you to look directly at the sun
and just blink every once in a while
and you can do that without any pain or discomfort
or watering of the eyes, please do that.
You're getting a lot of photons into your eyes
and they're transmitting that to your brain
and your brain to the rest of your body and on and on.
However, if you find it uncomfortable
to look directly at the sun,
in that case, what you'll want to do is offset your gaze
to 10 or 20 degrees, which is nerd speak
for just a little bit to the right
or a little bit to the left
and get the sunlight into your eyes indirectly.
Okay, and I often also get asked,
well, can I stand in the shade while I do this?
What if I have an overhang in my apartment?
The best thing is of course going to be
to face directly to the sun
and look either directly at it or slightly offset.
But if you can only get morning sunlight
by going out onto your balcony
and your balcony doesn't face east, rather it faces west,
you'll still get a lot of photons from the sun
reaching your eyes there.
But ideally you would find some way to look toward the sun
first thing in the morning.
I realized that with kids and work and other obligations,
this can be challenging,
but it is a challenge worth meeting.
Meaning don't lose your job
or forget to take care of your kids to do this,
but you can bring your kids to do this.
And indeed you should, it sets their circadian rhythms also.
And people often will ask, well, does it work on dogs?
You know, and indeed dogs and other animals
have these exact same circuits and pathways
for setting their circadian rhythm.
So it's great for them too.
Now there are also clear and documented benefits
for mood and mental health
to getting bright light in your eyes,
ideally from sunlight throughout the day,
as much as you safely can.
Please don't get sunburned,
don't get cataracts by getting too much sunlight,
but getting outdoors and getting sunlight in your eyes
during your lunch break or a walk here and there,
or if you have to remain indoors during the day,
getting the lights in that environment as bright as possible
as is safely possible, I should say,
is known to improve mood and mental health.
Why?
Well, because there's a special so-called opsin
within the cells of your eyes called melanopsin
that doesn't respond to the same differences in color
that are present in sunlight in the morning and the evening,
but rather responds to the overall brightness of light.
So very bright lights, either from artificial sources
or ideally from sunlight, activate these cells
and these cells project these little wires,
we call axons, into specific parts of the brain
that improve your mood and feelings of wellbeing.
So I can't give you a specific number
of five minutes a day or 10 minutes a day.
Just get as much light in your eyes,
ideally from sunlight throughout the day,
as is safe for you,
meaning where you're not getting sunburned
and you're not damaging your retina.
And if you want to know if you're damaging your retina,
well, anytime you have to blink or turn away from light
because it's really bright,
that's a signal that the light is too bright.
So while you want to place yourself into bright environments,
you don't want to place yourself into any environment
so bright that it's painful to be in.
Okay, so use that as a metric and you should be just fine.
And the last point about light for mood and mental health
is a relatively recent theme
that's emerging from the scientific literature
and that really was driven home by a recent study
that I mentioned a little bit earlier in the episode.
This is the study published in Nature Mental Health,
showing that darkness during a particular stage
of your 24 hour cycle,
your so-called circadian rhythm,
is also very beneficial for mood and mental health.
And it's beneficial for mood and mental health
in a way that is independent from light and from sleep.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Okay, well, there are a number of different ways
that this can be examined,
but in this particular study, which I like oh so much,
entitled Day and Night Light Exposure
are Associated with Psychiatric Disorders,
an objective light study in more than 85,000 people.
What the researchers did is they analyzed how much light
and or dark people were getting across the 24 hour cycle
and correlated that with mental health outcomes,
looking at a range of different mental health challenges,
including bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, depression,
PTSD, and much more.
And I'll go into this study in a lot of detail
in a future episode,
cause it's such an important study
with so many gems within it that we should all know about.
But one of the key things from this study
is that the positive effects of daytime sunlight exposure
and the positive effects of nighttime dark exposure,
that means of course the absence of light,
are independent of one another.
Put differently, making sure that you're in very dim
to completely dark environments
for a continuous six to eight hours
within every 24 hours circadian cycle
is correlated with much better mental health outcomes.
In other words, we shouldn't just think about
the presence of light in the morning
and throughout the day as positive for mental health.
That's all true, it's absolutely true.
And this study further verifies that,
but that's been known for some time,
indeed decades from the scientific research.
And of course it's been known for thousands of years
intuitively and subjectively
without detailed scientific measurement.
But in addition to that,
this study shows that people who stay in very dim
to dark environments for eight hours every 24 hours,
or I should say approximately eight hours
in every 24 hour cycle,
they benefit from improved mood and mental health outcomes
in a way that's independent of how much light they're getting
and independent of how much sleep they are getting.
The point is this, the time when you wake up,
consider that time zero.
And then about, again,
you don't have to be super strict about this,
about 16 to 24 hours after that wake up time,
you should be in a very dim to dark environment
for that 16 hour to 24 hour period after waking up, okay?
What do I mean by this?
I mean, if you go to sleep at 10 PM
and you wake up at 6 AM,
well that 10 PM to 6 AM phase of your circadian cycle,
you should be in very dim light
or entirely dark environment.
This is a great opportunity to reference another study
which was published in the proceedings
of the National Academy of Sciences,
which shows that even having a small amount
of light in the room, which isn't even that bright,
while you're sleeping with eyes closed
can disrupt morning glucose levels.
So in other words, keep your sleeping environment dark,
keep your nighttime environment dim
to the best of your abilities, right?
Certainly go out to dinner every once in a while,
go to the movies, go out and have a party, enjoy yourself.
If you have to go to the hospital, God forbid,
or you have to tend to some emergency, do that.
But to the extent that you can control it
within the confines of life and its demands,
keep your nighttime environment dim or dark
because that independently of any sunlight
and other bright light that you're viewing
during the daytime and afternoon
is going to positively improve your mood and mental health.
Now moving on to the other pillars
and these I'm going to move through a bit more quickly
than I have the previous two
because we've done entire series on these,
or I should say seriesies, seriesies?
Is that how you pronounce it?
Someone put the plural of seriesies
in the comments on YouTube.
The third pillar is movement.
And when I say movement, I mean exercise.
As you all know, we should all strive to get anywhere
from 180 to 220 minutes of zone two cardio per week.
That's movement that allows you to hold a conversation,
but were you to do it more intensely,
or even a bit more intensely,
you wouldn't be able to hold that conversation.
In addition, we should do some VO2 max work.
We should get our heart rate very high
at least once a week,
doing some sort of movement that's safe for you.
So that could be running or cycling or swimming
or Pilates, whatever it is for you,
getting your heart rate way, way up is also important.
And to do that at least once a week,
but daily movement, either cardiovascular training
or resistance training.
And it's very, very clear that we need both,
maybe not on the same days.
In fact, I split them to separate days.
Resistance training done for anywhere from six to 10 sets
per muscle group, either close to or to failure.
This could be with weights, it could be with bands,
it could be with machines.
All of that was covered in detail in the podcast series
that I did with Dr. Andy Galpin, an exercise physiologist
who's expert in all those areas.
I also did an episode on a foundational fitness protocol
that has been distilled into a very simple three page PDF
that you can get for completely zero cost
by going to hubermanlab.com
and just put foundational fitness protocol PDF
and you'll be taken to that toolkit.
So all of the details of a weekly exercise routine
that involves daily movement, but also certainly in my case
includes at least one full day of rest per week,
because many people do indeed need one,
maybe even two full days of rest per week.
So that highlights the third pillar movement,
but we know that cardiovascular training
and resistance training aren't just great for our body.
They also improve mood and mental health.
That's so very clear from the research literature.
So we can't overlook those in a conversation
about mood and mental health.
Now the fourth pillar is nutrition.
And nutrition is a big topic.
It's a very barbed wire topic.
If you get involved in this stuff online,
you know, you've got your people who believe that,
you know, carnivore is better than vegan.
You have the people who believe vegan
is better than carnivore.
Most people are omnivores.
You have your seed oil debates and on and on and on.
We're not going to touch any of that now.
Indeed, if you want to learn more about nutrition
and what works and what doesn't work
for sake of aesthetic changes, weight loss,
muscle gain, et cetera,
I would refer you to the guest episode
that we did with Dr. Lane Norton.
You can find that again at hubermanlab.com
where we do a deep dive on all the variations
and different nutritional protocols.
But suffice to say that regardless of whether or not
you're vegan, omnivore, carnivore, or keto or whatever,
everybody needs to consume sufficient amounts,
but not excess amounts of quality calories per day.
Now you may do that by intermittent fasting.
You may do that by a more traditional meal scheduling,
but everybody's going to need to do that
because your body and brain,
and indeed the parts of your body and brain
that translate to mood and mental health
require macronutrients,
proteins, fats, and carbohydrates,
as well as micronutrients.
So the key takeaway with nutrition
is to make it quality nutrition
within the bounds of whatever sort of nutritional program
that you're following.
And that means getting most of your food sources
from either non-processed or minimally processed foods.
So these will be foods that you're going to need to prepare
or foods that would perish over time.
These are not the sorts of foods that live in boxes
and cans and other packages
that would allow them to live on the shelves
forever and ever.
Okay, and as I say that, I know many people are shouting,
well, what about rice?
Rice can live on the shelf for a long time.
And yes, okay, I consider rice a minimally processed food
because of course it can live on the shelf
for a long period of time.
And here I'm just going to back out of the whole conversation
about nutrition at this point,
because as you can probably tell,
it's a deep series of rabbit holes that we can fall into
and really get distracted.
The point is make sure you're getting enough food.
Don't overeat.
We know energy toxicity is a problem
for not just body composition, but for mental health.
So you want to get enough calories, but not too few calories.
And you'll want to make sure that you're getting them
from quality sources.
And I say that because of course,
food is not just the substrate for the seller repair
and indeed production of tissues in your body,
but it's also the substrate for all the sorts
of neurotransmitters, right?
Which are derived from amino acid precursors
that are derived from food, right?
All of that dopamine stuff and serotonin stuff
is derived from amino acids that come from food sources.
So the link between nutrition and mental health
should now be an obvious one.
As we all know, quality nutrition influences,
of course, our physical health,
but also our mental health and our cognitive functioning,
our memory, our ability to learn new things and to focus.
And we know that one of the most important features
of high quality nutrition is making sure
that we get enough vitamins and minerals
from high quality, unprocessed or minimally processed sources,
as well as enough probiotics and prebiotics and fiber
to support basically all the cellular functions in our body,
including the gut microbiome.
Now, I, like most everybody,
try to get optimal nutrition from whole foods,
ideally mostly from minimally processed or non-processed foods.
However, one of the challenges that I
and so many other people face
is getting enough servings of high quality fruits
and vegetables per day, as well as fiber and probiotics
that often accompany those fruits and vegetables.
That's why way back in 2012,
long before I ever had a podcast, I started drinking AG1.
And so I'm delighted that AG1
is sponsoring the Huberman Lab podcast.
The reason I started taking AG1
and the reason I still drink AG1 once or twice a day
is that it provides all of my foundational nutritional needs.
That is, it provides insurance
that I get the proper amounts of those vitamins,
minerals, probiotics, and fiber
to ensure optimal mental health,
physical health, and performance.
If you'd like to try AG1,
you can go to drinkag1.com slash Huberman
to claim a special offer.
They're giving away five free travel packs
plus a year supply of vitamin D3K2.
Again, that's drinkag1.com slash Huberman
to claim that special offer.
The fifth pillar in the big six is social connection.
And we're going to talk a little bit more
about this later in the episode,
but let's just be very brief and specific about this.
We all need to strive to limit the number
of social interactions that we feel tax
or even vex us that cause us stress.
This is something that was covered in depth
in the episode with Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett,
where she talked about the fact
that we don't just have a nervous system
that regulates itself through experience
and through our thoughts and our actions.
We are, as a species, interacting with other nervous systems,
both of our own species, other humans,
as well as non-human species, dogs and cats,
and if you have them, horses and other animals.
So we need to think about our nervous system
as being both regulated from the inside
and through our own actions and choices and thoughts,
but also through interaction with other nervous systems.
And while we don't always have as much control
over which social interactions or work interactions
we have to engage in,
we should really strive to understand
and indeed pay some serious attention
to whether or not certain types of social interactions
are what she referred to as net savings,
neutral or taxing, right?
Certain types of social interactions
with certain people or groups of people
just make us feel taxed.
It makes us feel stressed.
It leads to negative affect.
That is not good feelings or emotions
and often elevated levels of autonomic arousal
that leave us ruminating
and leave us having challenges with sleep.
We really should all strive to limit those interactions
to the extent that we can.
On the reverse side of that,
as Lisa Feldman Barrett so beautifully pointed out,
we also have the capability
to regulate each other's nervous systems
in ways that produce savings,
that is, that allow us to feel
and indeed cause physiological changes
that make us feel not just happier, not just relaxed,
not just happy because we enjoy interacting with somebody
but we're a group, but that give us a savings,
that give us the kind of resources,
literally metabolic and neurochemical resources
that make us feel more capable
and give us a sense of elevated mood
and improved mental health
when we are not engaging with those people.
And this is highly subjective, of course,
but you should be able to distinguish.
In fact, I encourage you to spend a little bit of time,
maybe even just five or 10 minutes,
thinking about who are the individuals and groups
that I interact with that leave me feeling taxed,
that really seem to drain my energy
and have me ruminating and in a not good space
when I leave whatever interaction I had with them.
This could be a real interaction or an online interaction.
Indeed, I did this the other day based on Lisa's suggestion.
I found it to be tremendously useful.
What I did is I decided to,
and by the way, this was happening on a run
where I was thinking,
a lot of my mind is in a conversation with people
that aren't even here.
I was sort of working through a conversation.
I was thinking about what I would say,
what I did say, what they said,
in an interaction that unfortunately was pretty unpleasant.
It wasn't extremely unpleasant,
but it was pretty unpleasant.
And I realized, okay, that is a sort of interaction
that I would like to avoid in the future
because it wasn't happening right then,
but it was carried forward into a portion of my day,
my morning run that for me is normally very pleasurable
and quite sacred to me, actually.
So paying some attention
to how much of your internal dialogue is with yourself
versus with others and how much of that is positive
or negative is extremely beneficial.
And I'm not talking about always just thinking about oneself
and not thinking about others.
To the contrary, we also need to think,
as Lisa pointed out,
about who are the people with whom we interact with
or observe that lead us to have ongoing dialogue with them
in our mind or think about those interactions
in ways that give us energy,
that lead to energetic savings,
literally metabolic savings that we can apply,
not just in those interactions,
but in our work endeavors and our solo endeavors,
whatever that we're doing
when we are away from those people.
So while this concept of savings or neutral or taxation
of our metabolic and our neurochemical systems
might seem a little bit squishy, it is not squishy.
This is a neurobiological concept.
It's also a psychological concept.
And it's one that I'm so glad that Lisa brought up
because social connection, social interaction is so vital
to our mood and mental health.
But oftentimes we hear social connection and we think,
oh, that means we have to spend a lot of time with friends.
We have to organize dinner parties.
Well, sure, that's all fine and good if you can do that.
And I do, of course, encourage people to spend time
with those that they love,
but it's also important to take a step back
and just think a bit, maybe even write out a bit,
who are the groups and sorts of individuals
and interactions that really tax you?
Who are the people that you find kind of neutral?
And what are the individuals and groups
that really provide what Lisa referred to as savings?
That is, they tap into the metabolic
and neurochemical pathways that lead us
to have improved mood and mental health,
not just during those interactions,
but away from those interactions as well,
and often pervasively and extremely positively so.
So this is no small deal.
This is a really important aspect of our mental health.
Now, the sixth pillar in the big six is stress control.
And the reason it's included is that,
look, stress is going to happen.
Life is filled with so-called stressors.
And for a good number of years, in fact, the last 15 years,
there's been a lot of debate in the field of psychology
and neuroscience as well,
whether or not stress is good for us,
whether or not stress is bad for us,
whether or not we simply need to reframe stress
as good or bad.
And to some extent, all of that is true.
We know that chronic stress is not good for our memory,
our immune system, or our health.
We also know that if you understand the reality,
which is that stress also allows us to harness our mental
and physical resources to perform better than we would
otherwise in certain circumstances,
and that provided we can get to sleep each night,
that perhaps stress isn't so bad,
and perhaps is even performance enhancing.
I talked about this in the guest episode
with Dr. Ali Krum from the psychology department at Stanford,
and I've talked about this in other podcasts as well.
And I'm not here to tell you that stress is good for you.
I'm not here to tell you that stress is bad for you.
What I am going to tell you is that it is extremely important
that we all have readily accessible stress management tools
that work the first time and every time.
And these fall into two categories.
The first category are real time tools.
So tools that you can use to reduce your level of stress
in real time.
And the best way that I'm aware of that's grounded
in excellent physiology and neuroscience
to reduce your stress in real time
is the so-called physiological side.
I did not invent this pattern of breathing.
It's not breath work per se.
This is a pattern of breathing that we all naturally do
in our sleep to restore carbon dioxide and oxygen levels
to their proper ratios.
We also do it periodically throughout the day
without noticing.
Indeed, we have a defined or specific neural circuit
in our brain that extends to our diaphragm
and communicates with aspects of our heart, et cetera,
that allow physiological size to calm us down faster,
at least to my knowledge, than any other directed protocol.
And the physiological side, as many of you know,
is very simple and straightforward.
Anyone can do this.
You simply do a big inhale through your nose,
try and maximize the inflation of your lungs.
And then before you exhale,
sneak in another brief inhalation,
even if it's just a tiny micro inhalation
to maximally inflate the lungs.
And that has an important effect on the little sacs
in the lungs called the avioli of the lungs.
It's going to open up whatever avioli were collapsed
in there.
And then you're going to do a long extended exhale
through the mouth.
And typically just one,
although sometimes it requires two or three,
but just one physiological sigh is effective
in bringing down one's level of stress
significantly enough that you don't need to do it again.
So this can be done essentially anywhere and by anyone.
I suppose you probably couldn't do it if you were underwater
or certainly don't do it if you're underwater,
but otherwise it's a very safe and very effective way
to calm down and reduce your levels of stress
in real time, maybe before public speaking
or in whatever circumstance you feel you need to calm down
in real time.
So I'll demonstrate the physiological sigh for you here.
I've done this many times before in previous episodes,
but for those of you that haven't heard
or seen those episodes,
I feel obligated to do it again now.
Okay, so it's a deep inhale through the nose
followed by another brief inhale through the nose
and then a long exhale through the mouth.
And before you start asking questions about,
what do I do if I have a deviated septum?
Can it be just through the mouth?
Do the first two through the nose,
do the third through the mouth.
So it's like this.
And indeed I feel calmer.
And indeed, if you do it, you will feel calmer.
You'll notice that second inhale through the nose
was kind of sharp in the sense that I had to really push,
put some physical effort into making it happen.
And my shoulders jolted upwards
if you're just listening to this
and not watching my shoulders jolted upwards.
That second inhale through the nose is important
for a variety of reasons I've talked about elsewhere.
So the physiological sigh is going to be
the go-to protocol for you.
Again, not invented by me.
This is not Huberman breathing.
This is a pattern of breathing discovered in the 1930s
by physiologists.
It's hardwired into our nervous system.
And that's what makes it so great.
It works the first time and it works every time.
So that's, to my knowledge,
the best way to control your stress in real time.
Now, why is that important for mood and mental health?
Well, as we'll talk about later,
if you want to access your so-called generative drive,
a theme that we're going to get into in a bit more detail,
this is something that came up during the series
with Dr. Paul Conti,
you will learn that stress and anger and negative emotions,
while they can be very motivating, very arousing,
they are not going to be good
for your long-term mood and mental health, period.
So having tools to regulate your stress
and your levels of anger, your levels of reactivity,
and also to elevate your feelings of agency
and control over your life,
starting with agency and control over your physiology,
your internal state, is going to be vital.
And what I love about the physiological side
is that, of course, it's completely zero cost,
but also there's a dedicated circuit in your brain and body
for this particular pattern of breathing.
We do it spontaneously, but you can do it intentionally
and it works just as well, if not better,
to regulate your levels of stress.
That is to bring them down,
which has outsized positive effects
on your mood and mental health, not just in the moment,
but it also should improve your confidence
that when stress comes,
because the world is filled with stressors, it's not if,
it's when, when stress comes
that you will have a physiologically,
scientifically supported tool to deal with
and reduce that stress.
Now, in addition, I do believe it's important
for sake of mood and mental health
to also have a tool or a protocol
to raise your stress threshold.
That is to increase your capacity
to deal with life stressors
without them feeling so stressful.
And there are a number of different ways to do this,
but they all center around elevating your levels
of adrenaline, epinephrine, and norepinephrine,
noradrenaline, those are the same thing,
just they have multiple names, forgive me.
I didn't give the same two things four names,
so don't blame me, blame the other scientists that did it.
The point is, there are several ways
that you can self-induce elevations
of noradrenaline and adrenaline,
and then to learn to anchor your mind
and your thinking to stay calm
in those elevated adrenaline states
as a practice for when stressors hit you
in the outside world
and your adrenaline and noradrenaline spike.
Now, one of the best ways to do this,
because it works the first time and every time
and is also zero cost, in fact, it will save you money,
is to put yourself in a cold shower
or other deliberate cold exposure environment,
but most everyone has access to a cold shower,
not everyone, but most people.
And of course, by turning off the heat,
you're going to reduce heating costs, right, your water bill.
So getting into a cold shower for a minute or so
to elevate your levels of adrenaline
and learning to either use your breathing,
you could do physiological size,
or to distract yourself,
or whatever tools and approaches you need
to be able to stay calm
while you have elevated levels of adrenaline in your body.
And the reason deliberate cold exposure works so well
to do this is that it is pretty non-negotiable.
Even if you really love cold showers or cold plunges
or things of that sort,
you're still going to get that elevated adrenaline
and noradrenaline.
It's pretty much non-negotiable.
For the first 10 or 15 seconds
that you get into a cold plunge or a cold shower,
you should fully expect yourself to feel stressed
and for your breathing to accelerate.
And then your goal is to try and anchor
or control your breathing in that stressful environment.
The reason for doing this is that it's a practice.
It's a practice that's going to translate
to a better ability to manage your internal state,
and therefore your thinking, your cognition,
and your ability to make good decisions under stress.
It's not about becoming untouched by stress.
It's about being able to better navigate stress.
Indeed, I think of this as analogous to driving in fog,
something that I had to learn to do
because I grew up in the Bay Area
and it can be very foggy there sometimes.
And of course you don't learn to drive in fog
the first day you learn how to drive,
but the first time you hit heavy fog driving
where you can only see one reflector
in front of you at a time, it is truly stressful, right?
You don't know if you're going to come up
on another vehicle in an instant,
which of course can happen.
So you have to adjust a number of things.
You have to learn how to do that.
And while I would never elect to drive in fog,
learning to drive in fog teaches you
how to be comfortable driving
in different weather environments.
Same thing with driving in a rainstorm
or for you East coasters from the Northeast,
learning how to drive in a snowstorm.
You would never elect to do that,
but once you do it a few times,
you feel more comfortable in those extreme conditions.
So that's really what raising your stress threshold
is all about.
Of course, do it safely, do it under conditions
in which you're not going to get hurt
or anyone else will get hurt.
But learning how to do this can be extremely beneficial.
And of course, deliberate cold exposure isn't the only way,
but frankly, it's the most reliable way
and it's the most versatile way to do that
because you can do it in your shower
or in a cold plunge at home.
So you can practice these things.
Again, safety first,
always make sure you're not exposing yourself to cold
to the extent that you're going to damage yourself
mentally or physically, but it's a great practice.
And you could probably think of other ways
to spike your adrenaline that was safe.
And of course, life will spike your adrenaline.
So you can also use real life as your stress inoculation tool
and we all have to do that anyway.
What I'm suggesting is that you adopt a real time tool,
physiological size, and that you adopt
at least one offline tool that you do anywhere from one
to three, maybe seven days a week,
but at least one day a week that you put yourself
into a cold shower, deliberate cold exposure,
not for sake of increasing metabolism or anything else,
but really just to learn how to calm yourself
and maintain clear cognition when stress hits
because indeed stress is going to hit.
So that's the big six for improving mood and mental health.
And the big six apply, that is they are the cornerstone
for mood and mental health, regardless of who you are,
regardless of your age, regardless of whether or not
you're dealing with an acute or a severe mood
or mental health disorder, or you find yourself
to be reasonably healthy with respect
to mood and mental health.
And you simply want your mood and mental health
to be stable and or improve over time.
Now, the reason why the big six, those six pillars
are so important for mood and mental health
and indeed form a critical component
of what Dr. Paul Conti referred to
as the first principles of self-care
is that those six pillars establish a milieu
that is an environment of neurochemicals,
including neuromodulators such as dopamine, serotonin,
epinephrine, norepinephrine, acetylcholine,
and other neurochemicals as well, as well as hormones,
testosterone, estrogen, prolactin, cortisol,
and immune molecules and on and on
that lead to a high degree of predictability
in your brain and nervous system.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Why would predictability be such a key component
of mood and mental health?
Is it really just about knowing that you're going
to feel energized in the early part of the day
and tired at the end of the day?
Now, that might be part of it,
but that's not the major takeaway.
The major takeaway is that as Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett,
so aptly pointed out, your brain
and indeed your entire nervous system
has a couple of major jobs,
has the job of regulating your breathing
and your heart rate, et cetera.
It also has the job of regulating your thinking
and your planning and your memory.
Those are the jobs of the brain and nervous system
that we normally hear about.
But if we think about the more macro jobs
that the brain has, the key function of the brain,
certainly the parts of the brain
that are more recently evolved,
the ones involved in thinking and planning, et cetera,
are really involved in generating predictions,
predictions about what's going to happen next
and whether or not you're going to be prepared
for what's going to happen next.
And indeed, Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett
also beautifully illustrated this model
of the brain as regulating a brain-body budget
and moods and a related topic, which she called affect.
Okay, I'll explain what affect is in a moment.
Setting the stage for being able to better predict
what's going to happen next
and therefore regulating your mood in the moment.
Let's just take a moment and explore that statement
in a little bit more detail.
Essentially what she was saying
and what I'm now again saying
is that your brain and body go through different states.
Your state at a given moment can be labeled as your affect.
Your affect includes a lot of different things,
including levels of autonomic arousal,
levels of hormones, levels of trans mirrors,
all of that stuff.
But it falls under the umbrella of affect.
Affect essentially sets the stage for particular emotions
to be more likely or less likely to emerge.
So emotion and affect aren't the same thing.
Affect is a bit more general.
It sort of undergirds the possibility
of having certain moods like feeling elated,
happy or sad or depressed.
It really sets the general stage
for different types of specific emotions,
even highly specific emotions.
So in that way, when you're taking care of the big six,
when you're tending to these six pillars on a regular basis,
and I should point out that we really want to tend
to those six pillars every single day
or every single 24 hours,
we really need to make those a regular investment
to the extent that we can.
When we do that, we create a neurochemical
and a neural milieu that allows the brain
to be in a better predictive state.
It allows the brain to give rise to certain affects,
spelled A-F-F-E-C-T-S,
so affects that lead to certain emotions
being more or less likely to occur.
Put very simply, when we're tending to those six pillars
on a regular basis, we feel better more generally,
and therefore the emotions that we tend to have
under different conditions,
even conditions of a difficult interaction
with a coworker or with a family member,
tend to be more positive than if we are not tending
to those six pillars.
Now, in some sense, that's sort of a duh statement.
For instance, if you're sleep deprived,
if you're not fed well,
like you haven't eaten in a few hours,
of course, you're going to be more irritable,
you're going to be more reactive,
you are going to be more emotionally labile.
But sleep and nutrition
are just two of those six core pillars.
When we talk about those core pillars
and the necessity for tending to them
on a regular, every 24-hour basis,
what we're really talking about
is creating a milieu within our brain and nervous system
that allows the nervous system to do what it does best,
and in fact, what its main job is to do,
which is to predict what's going to happen next.
Because as Lisa Feldman Barrett pointed out,
emotions are really context-dependent states
that allow us to navigate not just our present circumstances,
but they are our nervous system and brain's best guess
about the circumstances that we are soon going to encounter.
Now, I don't offer you all of that
as kind of a bunch of a tangled mess of nerd speak
to confuse you.
What I'm saying is that by tending to those six core pillars,
you are shifting the likely affects that you will experience
and therefore the likely emotions that you will experience.
So you're biasing your whole system
towards more positive affect and more positive emotions,
regardless of what your life circumstances happen to be
and the stressors that you encounter.
And indeed, you also are including
that six pillar of stress control.
So when those stressors arrive,
you'll be better able to navigate them.
Now, this view of emotion regulation,
of mood and mental health,
is certainly not a novel concept.
People have talked about the physiological regulation of mood
from the time of William James and even earlier.
It's been a long-standing question, for instance,
or debate in psychology and philosophy.
Do we feel anxiety in our body and then label it as anxiety,
or do we feel anxiety in our mind and then our body follows?
That's been a long-standing debate
and frankly, there's evidence on both sides,
which leads me to the conclusion,
I think most neurobiologists and psychologists
to the conclusion that those things are interrelated
in a way that we can't really dissociate them completely
at any level, right?
When your heart rate goes up
and you start breathing faster,
if I were to induce that state in you,
you'd probably interpret that as feeling anxious.
In addition to that,
something can make you anxious
before your heart rate and breathing increases
and then your heart rate and breathing increases.
So no need to tease those apart.
But if you think about the brain,
in large part as a prediction machine
and your brain as a metabolic regulator,
it's trying to decide which organs need resources.
How much resource can I dedicate to thinking,
to creativity, to enjoying social interaction,
to paying attention to what somebody else is saying
as opposed to what's going on inside my body?
All of those major functions of the brain
as they relate to affect and emotions
are going to be best supported,
that is biased toward positive mood,
positive affect, positive emotions,
and therefore positive mental health outcomes
when we're tending to those six pillars.
Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett referred to that whole process
as the brain regulating a brain body budget.
And she had beautiful analogies for that budget.
And that's what led to the description
of social interactions as either generating savings
or being neutral or generating a taxed feeling,
literally taxing that brain body budget.
And I love that concept.
And it's one that you can keep in mind.
And indeed we can inject a lot of specificity
into this whole process of improving mood and mental health
through specific protocols.
If you simply remember,
if you make a daily investment in the six core pillars,
you are building up that brain body budget.
You will have more energetic resources to spend
on whatever life circumstances come your way.
Now, before we move into a discussion about protocols
for how to better understand your life narrative
to enhance your sense of self and confidence
and things of that theme,
I briefly want to mention that,
of course there are known tools out there
in the medical community and psychological community
for improving mood and mental health.
And while there are a variety of tools,
one of the main tools of the psychiatrist
is prescription drugs
that target specific neuromodulator systems
in the brain and body.
For instance, SSRI,
selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors
or atypical antidepressants
that target the dopamine and epinephrine systems
such as wellbutrin, bupryorone
or other types of antidepressants.
Or for instance, nowadays there's a lot of growing excitement
about clinical trials using relatively high dosages
of psilocybin, which by the way,
closely mimics the chemical serotonin.
That's right, psilocybin,
which is converted to psilocin in the brain.
If you look at it chemically,
it looks very much like serotonin
although it has distinct effects from serotonin.
I talked about psilocybin
and what's being done in terms of the clinical trials,
safety considerations.
I talked about the potential hazard considerations
and where the legality and all of that is going
in that episode if you want to check that out.
But the reason I'm taking a moment to mention these drugs,
things like SSRIs, Prozax, Olav, Citalopram,
wellbutrin, psilocybin and so on
is that all of them target specific neuromodulator systems
in the brain and body.
And at the same time, it's fairly clear
that mood disorders such as major depression
are not necessarily deficits
in things like serotonin or dopamine.
They can be, but most often they are not.
So why are such drugs prescribed for mood disorders
and for mental health disorders?
Well, because if specific neuromodulators
like serotonin, dopamine or epinephrine
are dramatically increased above baseline,
that affords the brain the ability to rewire itself.
Really the way to think about SSRIs
or atypical antidepressants or psilocybin
for the treatment of major depression
is really to think about them as chemical tools
to open or access neuroplasticity.
And that's why it's oh so important
that those drugs be combined with talk therapy
where people are actively working through the sources,
the real life sources and the historical sources,
maybe even the trauma-based sources of their depression.
And I mention this because there's a lot of debate nowadays
as to whether or not these drugs are useful,
whether or not the side effect profiles justify their use,
whether or not they are applicable to young populations.
There's a lot of debate about this.
And certainly in the case of the psychedelics,
there's a lot, a lot of debate
because this is a newly emerging area
and there's still not a lot of data,
although it's starting to increase over time.
But the key point here is that all of these drugs
have the potential to work in some people, not others.
Some people, they simply don't work for
and they cause more problems than solutions they solve,
but they tend to work by increasing the propensity
for neuroplasticity by changing the neuromodulator milieu
in the brain.
And this is an important point when thinking about tools
for enhancing mood and mental health,
that when we think about tools
for enhancing mood and mental health.
And next, of course, we're going to talk about the tools
that are specifically designed to target a specific aspect
of one's life story or concept of self.
All of that is always operating on a backdrop of two things,
that overall neurochemical milieu and autonomic function
that the six pillars relate to and support
if we're attending to those,
but any improvement in mood and mental health
that's going to be significant, it's going to be noticeable
and it's going to be stable,
it's going to be pervasive over time,
is going to require that some degree of neuroplasticity,
some degree of neural rewiring occur.
So I'm not bringing up the topic
of these particular drug tools to say that
they are the best way to improve mood and mental health.
I'm certainly not saying that.
They are, but one way to potentially improve
mood and mental health.
And if they are going to work,
they always work best when done in concert
with talk therapy,
because they are opening the opportunity
for neuroplasticity,
but then that neuroplasticity has to be directed
toward a particular endpoint.
There has to be specific work that's being done
by the individual or ideally the individual
with an expert trained clinically certified therapist
or psychologist or psychiatrist in order to make sure
that the neuroplastic changes that occur
lead to longstanding improvements
in mood and mental health over time.
Indeed, the drugs that I just described
were originally designed as tools to allow people
to access changes within their brain
that would then allow them to enhance mood
and mental health, but not have to rely
on the drugs themselves for improved mood and mental health.
And along those lines, I'm sure some of you out there
are thinking about the supplement-based
or nutrition-based approaches
to enhancing these neuromodulators.
And indeed, while they don't have the same potency
as things like Wellbutrin and SSRIs
at increasing things like dopamine
and serotonin respectively,
there is a growing number of people out there
that are relying on daily supplementation
with anywhere from one to three grams of L-tyrosine,
amino acid precursor to dopamine,
combined with often 300 to 600 milligrams of alpha-GPC
as a way to enhance dopamine and acetylcholine
and to set the stage for elevated levels of neuroplasticity.
But it's very important to point out
that the amino acid precursors
to the various neuromodulators like L-tyrosine,
like L-tryptophan, so L-tyrosine precursor to dopamine,
L-tryptophan precursor to serotonin, and so on,
that those don't have the same degree of potency,
that is ability to enhance those neuromodulators.
And so the extent to which they enrich the possibility
for neuroplasticity still remains somewhat obscure.
There haven't been clinical trials on that yet,
at least not clinical trials that I am aware of.
So I mentioned all of that stuff about drugs,
whether or not it's psychedelics
or whether or not it's prescription antidepressants
or whether or not people are using
a supplement-based amino acid-based protocol
for increasing certain neuromodulators.
I feel it was important to mention all of that because,
well, first of all, it's quite prominent out there,
certainly in the case of prescription antidepressants,
and there's growing prominence
and use of relatively high dose psilocybin.
Again, always done with support talk therapy.
This is done in a legal setting.
I said legal, not illegal,
a legal setting with a board-certified therapist.
This is being done on university campuses,
within research labs.
And of course, I acknowledge that there are people
who are using these compounds
outside the realm of the university
clinical study environment.
So I mentioned these chemicals,
not because I'm pointing to them as the path
to improved mood and mental health.
They can be, but they aren't always,
and as I mentioned before,
they can sometimes cause problems
that lead people to wish that they hadn't taken them
or to decide to not take them any further,
a decision that absolutely has to be made
with a healthcare professional
who's well certified to do that.
But I'm mentioning these tools
because I want you to understand if they work, why they work.
And one key point that was really emphasized
by Dr. Paul Conti, who, as I mentioned before,
is a psychiatrist,
so he uses pharmacology in his practice,
although he uses other non-pharmacologic tools as well,
is that these pharmacologic tools are never to be viewed
as the be all end all of enhancing mood and mental health.
They are but one path to improving mood and mental health
and indeed should be viewed as a path
to getting people who are otherwise unable to engage
in those six core pillars,
those first principles of mental health,
to be able to do those things on a regular basis.
And then perhaps, based on a discussion with their clinician,
these people could come off those pharmacologic agents.
Maybe yes, maybe no.
It depends on the individual.
It depends on the circumstances.
But those core six pillars,
those first principles of mental health
that include but are not limited to those core six pillars
are absolutely essential.
There's no drug that can replace those core six pillars.
I'd like to take a quick break
and thank our sponsor, InsideTracker.
InsideTracker is a personalized nutrition platform
that analyzes data from your blood and DNA
to help you better understand your body
and help you reach your health goals.
I've long been a believer
in getting regular blood work done
for the simple reason that many of the factors
that impact your immediate and long-term health
can only be analyzed from a quality blood test.
A major problem with a lot of blood tests out there, however,
is that you get information back about metabolic factors,
lipids and hormones and so forth,
but you don't know what to do with that information.
With InsideTracker, they make it very easy
because they have a personalized platform
that allows you to see the levels of all those things,
metabolic factors, lipids, hormones, et cetera,
but it gives you specific directives that you can follow
that relate to nutrition, behavioral modification,
supplements, et cetera,
that can help you bring those numbers into the ranges
that are optimal for you.
If you'd like to try InsideTracker,
you can go to insidetracker.com slash Huberman
to get 20% off any of InsideTracker's plans.
Again, that's insidetracker.com slash Huberman.
Okay, so setting aside the core six pillars,
let's now talk about other tools for mood and mental health
that center around really what we more typically think of
when we think of mood and mental health, which is emotions.
When Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett was a guest on the podcast,
she said something that was really incredible,
and it's something that's strongly grounded
in excellent scientific data,
which is the more specificity that we can put
to labeling our emotions,
the better off we're going to be
in terms of our overall mental health.
Let me restate that.
The more specific language that we can put
to our own internal emotions,
even if that language is just to ourselves
in our own internal narrative,
we don't even have to speak out what those labels are,
the better that we're going to feel over time.
And indeed, this effect can be quite rapid.
And indeed, Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett has done research
on this very specific topic.
It's something that's referred to as emotional granularity.
So while some of us move through life
with a sort of what I call emojification of emotions,
you know, you got your happy face, happy,
your sad face, sad, you know, you're angry, depressed,
anxious, you know, those are labels for emotional states,
or you could think of them as affects or emotions.
I think of them as emotions, but they're not very specific.
They're pretty broad bins.
We say sad or depressed or super depressed
or super sad, anxious, panic.
And when we think of that as nuance,
but it's not very nuanced.
And Lisa's laboratory and other laboratories
have explored two things.
First, if people are asked to or encouraged
to put more granularity, more specificity
on what they're feeling,
then it seems that their levels of emotional processing
are better overall.
How does that translate to emotions?
Well, it translates to better overall feelings of wellbeing
when one is placing more specificity on positive emotions.
And the flip side is also true.
So this is important to know.
If one places more specificity on negative emotions,
it also can enhance one's kind of experience
of those negative emotions.
Now, that means that this is a two-sided blade, all right?
This isn't always a good thing.
And if one is thinking about protocols
for improving mood and mental health,
the data make very clear that adding more specificity
to our positive emotions in terms of the language we use,
but also just the depth with which we process
and think about those positive experiences
can be very beneficial for us.
So there are two studies that I'd like to highlight
that relate to this.
The first is entitled Effective Self-Monitoring
Through Experience Sampling
on Emotion Differentiation in Depression.
And the second study is entitled
Emotional Granularity Increases
with Intensive Ambulatory Assessment.
Methodological and individual factors influence how much.
Now, each of these studies focus
on something slightly different.
The first study was mainly focused
on people who have depression,
and they were cued several, if not many times per day,
to just think about and report on their emotional state.
And that was done in order to get people
to place more granularity,
more specificity on what they're feeling,
but also simply to tap into how they're feeling
on a more regular basis throughout the day.
The second study, which is one that included
Dr. Lisa Feldman-Behr as an author,
was slightly different because it focused
on non-depressed individuals,
and it cued them to touch into their emotions
more times per day,
and it also included some physiological measurements.
And one in particular that we're going to talk about
in some detail.
Now, I don't have time to go into all the details
of these studies.
I may do that in a future podcast episode,
but the key takeaways are very important
for all of us to know, which are, first of all,
the more often that you can ask yourself,
what am I really feeling right now?
How do I feel?
And, and this is so critical,
the more that you force yourself to not use broad labels
or simply valence labels.
Valence labels are good or okay or bad.
And instead, understand that good is not an emotion.
Okay is not an emotion.
Bad is not an emotion.
But rather saying, you know, I feel, you know,
curious but a little anxious,
if that happens to be the case.
Or I feel, you know, bored,
but, you know, also a little bit in positive anticipation
about what's going to happen tomorrow.
Things of that sort,
putting more nuance and specificity on your emotions,
but also touching into or thinking
about your own emotional states more times per day,
clearly has positive outcomes for mood and mental health.
And the reasons for that are incredibly interesting.
And this is something everybody should understand.
Why would it be that putting more specificity
on what we're feeling?
So perhaps just in our own heads,
like thinking, okay, how do I feel right now?
Like if I were to do that right now,
I'd say I feel energized
and happy.
I do, I really enjoy doing what I'm doing.
So I wouldn't say I'm like off the charts in awe
or elation, but I'm very happy and I feel energized.
You know, earlier today,
I was feeling a little bit fatigued
and a little bit confused
because I was trying to sort out something
and it wasn't making sense to me.
So assessments like that,
which can be told to somebody else
or that we just hold internally,
done repeatedly throughout the day,
anywhere from three to six times throughout the day,
just periodically pinging ourselves.
Maybe you set an alarm
or maybe you just decide to every once in a while,
maybe every time you go into an elevator
or every time you go up a flight of stairs,
you just ask yourself, yeah, how do I feel right now?
And thinking about that for a moment.
And you don't have to write it down,
although I suppose you could.
What turns out that just that practice
can really enhance our so-called emotional granularity
that can enhance our positive emotions and affect.
And in addition, it provides us a better sensitivity
to better understand those negative emotions,
which sounds like it might be a bad thing,
but those negative emotions have information in them.
Right, this is one thing that's often lost
in those broad categorizations of anxious
or sad or depressed.
And keep in mind, of course,
that some people are genuinely clinically depressed
and that needs to be taken extremely seriously,
just like some people are genuinely clinically anxious
and that needs to be taken seriously.
But most of us, when we throw out the words depressed,
angry, sad, we're not using enough nuance
and it doesn't really apply to our internal states
or the circumstances that we're in.
And as a consequence, we suffer.
It's not just about communicating our emotions,
we suffer because the data say that the more nuance,
the more emotional granularity that we have,
the richer is our experience of the positive aspects of life
and the more effectively we can navigate
the negative aspects of life, right?
Again, negative emotions perhaps isn't the best way
to even describe negative emotions
because that label negative implies that we should avoid it.
And in fact, those negative emotions
provide a lot of information about perhaps
social interactions that we should seek to avoid
in the future and so on and so forth.
Now, one of the most interesting things
about this whole process of increasing emotional granularity
and touching in several times per day
into how we feel, something that's completely zero cost,
takes just a moment to do,
that we can get much better at over time.
That was clearly seen in these studies
that people get much better at doing this.
It becomes more facile for them very quickly
is that it correlates with improvements
in physiological metrics that relate
to overall improvements in mood and mental health.
And the specific physiological metric that I'm referring to
is so-called vagal tone.
Some of you have perhaps heard of the vagus nerve.
It's the 10th cranial nerve.
It's an extensive peripheral nerve
that it goes out of the brain at the level of the neck.
It's one of the cranial nerves that extends
to essentially all the organs of the body,
the heart, the lungs, et cetera, but it's a two-way street.
It's a superhighway of nerves out of the brain
and into the body, and it's a superhighway of nerves
back from the bodily organs to the brain.
And it's involved in regulating a lot of
so-called autonomic functions.
So how fast our heart rate is,
how fast our breathing is, rates of digestion.
And all of that weaves together to create those things
that we call affect our internal states.
So without going into a ton of detail about the vagus nerve,
there's something that's called cardiac vagal control.
Cardiac vagal control is the extent to which
that vagus nerve can impact your heart rate
and your overall feelings of calm or alertness.
Now, the simple way to think about this
is more commonly referred to as heart rate variability.
Heart rate variability is simply the distance
between your heartbeats,
or rather the time between your heartbeats,
which we know if those timings between your heartbeats
are somewhat variable,
that is correlated with positive physical
and mental health outcomes.
One of the ways that you can increase heart rate variability
is to get regular cardiovascular exercise,
as well as doing resistance exercise,
and no surprise, getting sufficient amounts
of quality sleep each night is also going to be
very beneficial for heart rate variability.
Now, exercise and sleep, of course, are wonderful,
but it turns out that there's also a very rapid way
to increase heart rate variability
by activating the vagal innervation of the heart
and the way that the heart and some other circuits
within the so-called brainstem interact.
And that's through something called respiratory sinus arrhythmia.
Respiratory sinus arrhythmia can be summarized very simply
by saying when you inhale, you speed your heart rate up,
and when you exhale, you slow your heart rate down.
And it's that exhale, slowing your heart rate down
that's mediated by the vagus nerve.
Now, there's a more thorough description of that,
which I'll just give you now, and it's not that lengthy.
So here's how it goes.
When you inhale, your diaphragm actually moves down,
and as a consequence, your heart actually gets a little bigger,
has a little more space.
As a consequence, the fluid in your heart
moves a little more slowly per unit volume,
and there's a neural signal to speed the heart up.
Conversely, when you exhale, the diaphragm moves up.
That means there's a little less space for the heart
in the general area where it's sitting,
so the heart gets a little bit smaller,
a little more compact.
That means that the fluid in your heart
is moving more quickly through that smaller space,
and there's a neural signal mediated by the vagus
to slow the heart down.
So that's why inhale, speed your heart up,
and exhales, slow your heart down.
That is the basis of so-called RSA,
or respiratory sinus arrhythmia.
Now, what does any of that have to do
with the granularity of language
that we place on our emotions?
Turns out there's several studies showing
that when people place more descriptive granularity
on their emotions, that is correlated with, okay?
It's not causal, but it's correlated with improvements
in respiratory sinus arrhythmia,
which we know correlate with improvements
in heart rate variability.
Indeed, it's one of the major bases
for heart rate variability,
which we know is correlated
with not just positive physical health outcomes,
but positive mental health outcomes,
including lower levels of anxiety, improved sleep,
and overall levels of mood.
This is a topic that I'm very familiar with,
because last year, my laboratory
at Stanford University School of Medicine
in collaboration with a colleague of mine,
Dr. David Spiegel, our Associate Chair of Psychiatry,
also at Stanford University School of Medicine,
published a clinical trial in Cell Reports Medicine,
showing that there's a particular pattern of breathing
that people can do for just five minutes per day
that is effective in significantly improving
various metrics related to mood, and reducing anxiety,
and also improving sleep.
Although I should say the protocol I'm about to describe
didn't uniformly improve all of those metrics.
It had a bigger effect on some versus others.
I'll provide a link to that study in the show note captions.
But if you're wondering what this protocol is
that people did for five minutes a day
that allowed them to, by the way,
pervasively improve their mood.
So it wasn't just their mood
while they were doing this five minute a day protocol.
It was improvements in mood around the clock, essentially,
as well as improvements in other physiological metrics
and other aspects of those six core pillars.
It was that physiological sigh that we talked about earlier.
Although in this case,
we didn't have people do just one physiological sigh.
We had people set aside five minutes per day.
So set a timer for five minutes.
They could sit or lie down.
They could do it any time of day.
And we just had them repeat that physiological sigh
for a duration of five minutes total
so that they would do two inhales through the nose,
and then a full exhale to lungs empty through the mouth.
Then they would do it again,
and then they would do it again.
And again, until those five minutes were completed.
Again, the outcome of that clinical trial
was that that particular pattern of breathing,
which we called cyclic physiological sighing
for five minutes per day,
again, done any time of day,
had the most positive outcomes
in terms of improving mood and mental health
and autonomic function,
those things related to sleep and heart rate variability.
So that's a very simple, very minimal time investment,
zero cost tool that anyone can use
that again improves various metrics of physical health,
but also improves metrics of mental health.
And it ties right back in with what was observed
in the work by Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett,
exploring how putting more word label,
emotional granularity on one's emotional states
positively impact our physiological state.
And the fact that thinking about our emotions
more frequently throughout the day
and deliberately putting more label granularity
on those emotions frequently throughout the day
is correlated with this improvement
in respiratory sinus arrhythmia and heart rate variability.
The fact that these things all relate to one another
should not surprise us because indeed
there's a previous paper,
this is a quite extensive review.
Actually, it's a very nice review.
It's one that I encourage anyone who's interested
in these topics to explore,
especially psychologists who might have a interest
in physiology or psychiatrists
or simply people who are interested in mind-body stuff.
This is a review published in 2017
in the journal, Biological Psychology,
entitled Cardiac Vagal Control
as a Marker of Emotion Regulation in Healthy Adults,
a review.
And again, it's a really wonderful literature review
of the peer-reviewed primary research,
which really establishes that this thing, vagal tone,
our ability to kind of put the brakes
on our autonomic nervous system
and slow our heart rate down deliberately
through our breathing,
and perhaps even just by stopping and reflecting
on what our emotional states are
is really beneficial for our overall mood
and mental health.
And I want to highlight, bold,
and underline that word overall,
because it's not just the case
that people experience elevated mood and mental health
in the moments where they stop and go,
oh, how am I feeling?
Oh, you know, am I feeling bored or agitated?
Do I feel particularly excited?
Sure, that can have some impact on physiological metrics
and mood and mental health,
but in all of these studies,
the outcome seems to be that people's overall levels
of mood and mental health are enhanced,
not just while they're thinking about their emotions
or doing this five-minute-a-day cyclic sighing,
but around the clock, which is really terrific
because I think that's what most all of us want,
which is improved mood and mental health,
not just in the moments when we do a practice
or in the few minutes afterwards,
but 24 hours a day.
I suppose we might segment out sleep
during which, you know, hopefully we're having great dreams
as opposed to other kinds of dreams.
But the point is everyone, I have to imagine,
would like to feel better
and have elevated mood and mental health
during the times when they're awake.
And indeed, these sorts of protocols
have been shown to do that,
or so say the scientific data.
Now we are going to discuss the tools
for enhancing mood and mental health
gleaned from the four-episode guest series
with Dr. Paul Conti,
who is a medical doctor specializing in psychiatry.
He also has particular expertise in trauma.
However, the four-episode guest series
that we did with Dr. Conti
was really about exploring the self,
as well as tools and protocols
for not just gaining a better understanding of oneself,
but also for gaining a better understanding
and tools for relating to others, AKA relationships.
Thread through the series was a model of the mind
and how it works to create everything
from feelings, thoughts, to behaviors
that Dr. Paul Conti described as an iceberg model.
And I perhaps should refer you to the fact
that he actually drew out this model
and we provided it as a zero-cost PDF
in the show note captions
for every single one of those episodes
in that four-episode series.
We also provide a link to this model
in the show note captions for this tools episode.
The model is called the iceberg model.
And as the name suggests, it resembles an iceberg
in which the vast majority of our mind's processing
occurs below our conscious awareness in our unconscious mind.
So that's the portion of the iceberg
that resides below the surface.
Whereas the portion of our mental processing
that we are aware of resides above the water surface,
the so-called conscious mind.
So a key aspect of the iceberg model
is that the unconscious mind is responsible
for the vast majority of our feelings,
thoughts, and behaviors,
but that we are not aware
of how this unconscious mind is doing that.
And by extension, the tools and protocols
that Dr. Conti described,
largely deal with going into the unconscious
and figuring out how the unconscious processing
is influencing our conscious processing,
both in healthy and in unhealthy ways.
And when we say in healthy and unhealthy ways,
we're largely referring to the presence of defenses.
So some of you have perhaps heard of defenses before.
Some defenses can indeed be healthy
and others are unhealthy.
There are defenses such as projection, sublimation, denial.
And during the course of that four episode series,
Dr. Conti explains how projections
are not always bad for us.
Indeed, they can protect us from panic, from severe trauma,
but they also can create difficulties
in processing our own understanding of self
and of our life experiences
in ways that can actually be damaging to us.
So a key takeaway from that four episode series
is to understand and acknowledge
that your unconscious mind is driving
much of what you feel, think and do.
However, by doing structured exploration of the self,
and we'll talk about how to do that,
one can gain better understanding
of how that unconscious processing
is influencing what you think, feel, believe and do.
So once you accept the important role of the unconscious mind
and you make the decision that you want
to better understand how your unconscious mind
and conscious mind are in this constant dialogue
and how you can have that dialogue better serve you,
there are a series of actionable tools that you can do
that will allow you to better understand yourself
and how you relate to others.
And the first of these tools
is to really understand your self concept.
Now, of course, most all of us know our own name.
Rarely do we ever forget that name.
We have some concept of where we're from,
who our parents are, what our present and future goals
might be, where we've succeeded,
where we failed in life and on and on.
But the self concept goes far beyond
that sort of CV list or our biography of self.
Indeed, the self concept has a lot to do
with our self confidence, our feelings of ability,
both to overcome challenges,
but also our ability to serve the world that we're in
and our ability to change ourselves over time.
Now, of course, the degree to which somebody
might have confidence or less confidence
or the degree to which somebody feels
that they can exert influence on their environment
and their goals is of course going to vary
based on their personal history.
But as Dr. Conti explained, even independent of all that,
if one puts in some work to better understand
their self concept, to really get a clear picture
of one's self, from that one can develop more agency
with which to pursue one's aspirations
and to reach their goals.
And the key concept here is one that's particularly powerful
for both exploring and building up one's concept of self.
And that's to consciously and deliberately build
a life narrative.
Now, a simple way to do this that can be very effective
is to create a series of folders or documents.
It could even be a stack of papers.
I prefer to do this in electronic form.
And I confess that even before learning about this tool
from Dr. Conti, I had initiated doing this tool
starting back in 2015.
And it's fairly straightforward, but as I mentioned before,
it can be very powerful.
And it simply consists of building out separate folders
or pieces of paper, and this could be done electronically
or on real world paper with paper and pen
or paper and pencil.
And essentially what you do is you're going to divide
your life history into some regular increments.
So for me, the way that I did this is I created a folder
on my laptop that I actually call Lifetime.
So that's the title of the main folder.
And then within that folder, I have a series of folders,
each of which spans a particular phase of my life.
So zero to five years of age, six to 10 years of age,
11 to 15 years of age, and so on and so forth.
Now I'm 48 years old, so I have folders that extend
to age 50 currently, although I will add folders
going forward very soon.
And the idea here is that for each of those folders,
you're going to place a single word document
into that folder.
And then on that word document, you're not going to journal,
you're not going to do any sort of extensive writing,
rather you're simply going to put down bullet points
with titles, it could be one or two sentences,
but typically it's just a few words describing
some of the key milestone events that you remember
from that particular phase of your life.
So just for sake of example, I'll read off some
of the things that are included in the folders
for my particular lifetime narrative.
But of course, this relates to my lifetime narrative,
you should of course, put the milestones
and key bullet points that relate to your lifetime narrative.
But again, just to give you a sense of the sorts of things
that made it into this folder,
in my six years old to 11 year old folder,
on that document, I put where I was living at that time,
the city I was living, the school that I went to,
I put a couple of teachers names,
teachers that had a particular influence on me,
a particular summer camp experience,
that was not a traumatic experience by the way,
it was a happy experience, but for me,
it turned out to be a very transformative one.
And then there were a couple other things in there
that are just recollections of childhood friends names.
So seemingly mundane information perhaps,
but it looks more or less like a biography
and yet other folders.
So for instance, the folder that spans from 25
to 30 years of age is the time that I was
in graduate school, so it includes a note
about graduate school, a note about particular hobbies
that I was interested in,
in addition to my scientific research at the time,
a couple of key relationships,
a couple of key relationship challenges,
as well as some things that at that time,
I was processing about prior years,
in particular my teen years in high school.
Now, the key thing here is that whatever goes
into these folders is what's important to you.
It could be positive events, it could be negative events.
It could be events that for whatever reason you remember
and that keep surfacing in your mind
that you think might be interesting or important
at some later time or that you're concerned
you might forget.
In fact, that might be a really good metric
for whether or not you include something
in these folders or not.
If there's something that you want to make sure
that you never forget, but that you think you might forget,
I would encourage you to put it onto that word document
and put it into that particular folder.
Again, this isn't about creating a coherent life story.
This is about creating a series of segments
of small collections of key life events,
positive, negative, neutral, inspiring,
basically anything that was salient for you
at that particular time.
And of course, if you want to put reflections
about those particular events into that word document,
you're more than welcome to do that.
But the basis of this self-concept developing exercise
is just that, it's to develop a historical sense
of yourself.
Of course, bringing you up to present day
where you will continue to add things
to whatever word document goes into that particular folder
for the age you happen to be now.
Now, for some of you,
this kind of autobiographical bullet pointing
might seem like it's just that,
some attempt to build or write an autobiography.
But it's very important to remember
that these folders are for you.
These folders are not about writing a book
about your life history.
Although if you decide to do that with these folders
at some point down the line, that sounds great,
but that's not the goal here.
The goal is for you to build a structured,
narrative representation of events
that were key in your life.
And as described in the series with Dr. Conti,
this goes way beyond just understanding your past.
This is really about understanding past.
It's about understanding yourself at present.
And indeed it threads into your goals
and aspirations for the future.
An important thing to understand about this tool
or protocol is that it also has a incredible ability
to anchor you in your perception of the passage of time.
Some of us track the passage of time better than others,
both within the day and across days and years and so forth.
But this exercise in particular is very good
at allowing you to see how much time you devoted
at a given stage of your life to a given endeavor,
whether or not you're stuck in patterns
whereby you're still engaging
in certain types of things professionally
or relationship wise,
or in any other number of different ways
that have you in a pattern
that may or may not be serving you well.
I want to emphasize again that this exercise
is not about goal setting.
It's about your ability to build
a structured narrative pattern
from which you can look at it
and then make a determination as to whether or not,
you feel that you're currently on the right path for you.
But it's not about projecting forward
as to what your goals are.
We'll soon talk about that.
We'll talk about goals and aspirations in a moment.
This is really about better understanding
what led you up to the place that you are now.
And it really helps you pinpoint the key work
that you need to do in terms of exploring your unconscious
and conscious mind using some tools
that we're going to get into subsequently.
So there's really no strict rules
about how to do this exactly,
except that I do encourage you to make those increments
across your lifespan manageable.
I wouldn't suggest doing it one for every year.
I wouldn't suggest a folder, one for every 10 years.
I think a three to five year increment
seemed like a more reasonable
and tractable way to go about this.
So that's one of the sorts of tools
that Dr. Conti referred to
as to how to build up one's self-concept,
which directly relates to things such as our confidence,
our ability to track our own behavior,
understand some of our motivations,
both conscious and unconscious.
But of course, that practice is mainly a conscious exercise.
It's really not tapping directly into the unconscious
in any kind of direct way as far as we know.
Now we can contrast that with the tools and protocols
that are designed to tap into the unconscious mind.
And of course, there are a number of different ways
to do this that were discussed
in that four episode series with Dr. Conti.
But one of the most powerful ways to do this
is by thinking about and indeed sometimes writing about
or even analyzing one's dreams.
Now dream analysis is something
for which you can find a lot of books out there.
There are a lot of theories.
There's also a lot of argument that perhaps dream analysis,
which has roots in Freudian psychology,
as well as other traditions is perhaps not accurate.
I don't think we want to consider
whether or not dream analysis is accurate.
Rather, I think we should just acknowledge
that when we are dreaming,
in particular the dreams that we have
toward the later part of our night,
which are the dreams associated
with rapid eye movement sleep
that tend to be very emotionally late in dreams
as compared to the dreams that we have earlier in the night.
Well, when we consider the content of those dreams,
even if we're not trying to interpret them,
it's very clear that those dreams reflect
the unconscious mind controlling more
of our internal dialogue
or what we are experiencing at that time.
Whereas when we are awake,
our conscious mind tends to take over more of the narrative,
the internal narrative and the control
of our feelings, thoughts and behaviors.
But as I mentioned before,
the unconscious mind is always exerting an influence
regardless of whether or not we are asleep or awake.
With that said, one way to explore the unconscious mind
and to begin to get a better understanding
about how it might be influencing
our waking states and behaviors
is to actually record and think about one's dreams.
Now, of course, some people remember their dreams
on a regular basis, other people don't.
Some people actually believe that they don't dream.
Studies out of sleep laboratories at Stanford,
University of Pennsylvania, Harvard and elsewhere
all generally agree that everybody dreams,
but not everybody remembers their dreams.
So if you're interested in tapping into an understanding
of what your dreams are telling you,
which is basically a way of saying
what your unconscious mind or dialogue consists of,
I highly recommend putting a journal.
So this would be any kind of paper and pen
or paper and pencil type journal.
And the idea is this, if you wake up
and you can remember your dream,
write down a few key bullet points from that dream.
If you feel you can write out the dream
in a very linear narrative, this happened,
then that happened, then this happened,
then that happened, great.
But most people find that their memory of their dream
is rather fragmentary.
Other people can't remember their dream,
or at least they wake up,
they feel like they were having a dream,
but they can't remember all of it or key components of it.
And for that, I suggest that you try keeping your body
completely still and closing your eyes once again.
We don't quite understand why this is,
but when you look at the literature on dream recollection,
it seems that by keeping one's body completely still
with eyes closed, we have better access
to whatever the contents of the dream
that just occurred were, okay?
So if you wake up and you can't remember your dreams,
try lying still for a few minutes
and keeping your eyes closed and seeing whether or not
that helps surface the content of that dream.
Other people find that they get up, they get out of bed,
and then sometime in the middle of the morning,
maybe even later in the day,
the contents of a dream will just come to them.
Well, if that happens, great.
I also highly recommend that you have a way to write down
the contents of that dream.
Now, what you're looking for
when you do this sort of tool or protocol,
I encourage you to be wary of any immediate interpretation
of, for instance, okay, animals in a dream mean children,
although they could.
There's not a lot of science that really supports that
as a firm statement.
And of course, there are books out there and podcasts
and a ton of information
trying to help you interpret your dreams.
And while some of that can be fun
and not all of it is entirely useless,
the goal here is not to interpret your dreams.
The goal here is to start recording
some of the key takeaways,
maybe even the entire narrative of the dreams
that you have just prior to waking
as a way to try and understand some of the themes
that are occurring and recurring in the dialogue
that exists within your unconscious mind.
So a key aspect of this tool is that
you're not going to take any one dream
as an enormously informative dream.
It might be, but more important in this particular tool
is to write down the themes of a particular dream
and then see whether or not those particular themes
resurface again and again across different nights
or across different dreams.
The idea here is that things that are repeating thematically
will show up as different components in different dreams,
but that by keeping a dream journal,
you can start to identify some of these patterns
that are occurring from one dream to the next
as opposed to having the same dream over and over.
But the point here is that you can explore the contents
and the themes, that's really the most important word here,
the themes of your unconscious mind that is occurring
if you start thinking about what's recurring
during your dreams, because dreams are a time
when your unconscious mind is dominating the narrative
within your mind and brain.
Now, for those of you that dream a lot
and remember your dreams,
as well as for those of you that do not,
I would also encourage you to explore the contents
of your thinking, that is thinking about your thinking
during so-called liminal states.
And the liminal state during which this can be
particularly useful is right upon waking.
So this is different than thinking about
what you were dreaming about.
This is about keeping your eyes closed and body still.
We do think that that's important for doing this well,
because once you start moving your body,
you open your eyes and you start bringing in
sensory experience for that day,
your mind dramatically shifts towards conscious processing.
But in that liminal state between sleeping and awake,
when you wake up and you're a little sleepy,
maybe you don't want to get out of bed,
and this happens to me all too often,
try closing your eyes and remaining perfectly still
for maybe one to three minutes, maybe five minutes,
and just pay attention to where your mind goes.
Now, you might fall back asleep, be mindful of that,
depending on what you need to do that morning.
But a lot of people will find that their mind goes into
this place that's neither sleep nor awake, right?
This is a state that very much resembles the state
people achieve in things like yoga nidra, yoga sleep,
or in non-sleep deep rest,
although it tends to be more dominated
by the unconscious mind, a little bit more sleep-like.
Now, some people find this practice to be difficult
because they're the sort of people that wake up
and they're just immediately ready to go.
Most people, however, myself included,
find that when they wake up,
the mind isn't completely alert yet,
and you can use that period,
again, just maybe two or three minutes, maybe five minutes,
to start to pay attention to the contents of your thinking,
see whether or not your thinking migrates from
something related to work or to relationship or to self
or to something you want to do
or something that you're anxious about and so on and so on.
And here too, you'll want to write this down.
So this is very much like the dream journaling
we just talked about,
but it's slightly easier for most people to access,
especially people who have a hard time
remembering their dreams.
And again, it's an opportunity to access
some of the contents of your unconscious mind,
to learn to look at and see what's going on
in your unconscious mind in a way that's very difficult,
if not impossible to do,
unless you're working with somebody who's very good
at accessing the unconscious,
such as a skilled psychiatrist or psychoanalyst,
and in that way, allowing you to do introspective work,
which is not structured in terms of thinking,
trying to think about like, what do I want?
What's going on?
Why did they do that?
Why did I react that way?
Nothing like that.
You're simply observing your mind
and seeing what's geysering up from the unconscious.
That is, you're getting a portal
into that portion of the iceberg
that resides below the surface of the water.
The next set of tools for exploring the self,
self-concept, et cetera,
from that four episode series with Dr. Conti is journaling.
I'm going to do an entire episode
of the Huberman Lab podcast about journaling.
And there are a lot of different kinds of journaling
and fortunately, there are a lot of great
peer-reviewed studies about the power of journaling
for processing all sorts of things
like emotional states, trauma, et cetera.
There are basically two categories of journaling
that are very useful to carry out on a consistent basis.
And when I say consistent basis,
that could mean every day,
or it could mean three times a week,
it could even be once a week.
There are really no hard and fast rules about this,
but when we think about journaling,
there are really two main styles of journaling.
One is going to be free associative journaling.
Sometimes people talk about this as a data dump, right?
Typically, people will talk about the data dump
as the morning notes,
which is when you wake up in the morning,
you've got a lot on your mind,
you can't organize your mind.
People who have a hard time structuring their thinking
and behavior often find this very useful,
which is to take out a journal or a piece of paper.
Again, this is just for you.
It's important that you realize
and really make sure that you're the only person
that's going to see these notes,
because a lot of people get into self-monitoring
when they're doing their journaling.
They're thinking about, well, how's this going to look?
Is my handwriting okay?
How's my punctuation?
What are people going to think?
Is this going to be a good book or not a good book?
Listen, none of this journaling that we're referring to
is about your book or your autobiography.
This is really just for you.
This is an exploration of yourself
that's designed to help you enhance your concept,
that is your understanding of self,
and indeed translates to better confidence,
better understanding of your goals and aspirations,
better understanding of your unhealthy patterns
and defenses and on and on.
And so again, the two styles of journaling
are free association.
So where you literally just write down
anything that comes to mind
or that you feel like writing down
within a given period of time.
For most people, 10 minutes is ample time to do that.
For some people, five will be enough.
And for some who have the time, maybe 30 minutes.
But for me, and I think for most people out there,
anywhere from five to 10 minutes
of this data dump free association,
it could be your anxieties, what you're thinking about,
what you're anxious about.
Really could be about anything that comes to mind.
And this free association process can be very useful
for clearing out the clutter, so to speak.
The other style of journaling that's equally useful,
but for different reasons, is structured journaling
to have a goal for a given entry on a given day.
And again, this could be done in the morning,
afternoon or night.
And the idea would be that you would set an intention,
and by intention, I mean a specific topic
that you're going to restrict your writing to.
And that writing should be about self,
in particular goals and aspirations.
What you've wanted in the past, yes,
but also what you want at present,
what you might want in the future for yourself.
These could of course be material things,
but in general, this is more about aspirations
of things that you would like to accomplish or generate.
And the key word there is generate.
And if you listen to the four episode series
with Dr. Conti, he talked about three drives
that exist in all of us.
These three drives are the aggressive drive,
the pleasure drive and the generative drive.
And we don't need to go into a lengthy description
about these drives right now.
If you're curious about them and what they represent
and how they can be in balance or out of balance
and how that serves us or doesn't serve us,
please check out that four episode series
with Dr. Conti, because he goes into that
in a fair amount of detail and also in an actionable way.
But the key thing here is that we're generative.
One of the things that I asked Dr. Conti at the outset
and throughout the entire series was,
what is mental health?
We talk about physical health and we have some idea
of what that represents, healthy blood pressure,
the ability to do certain forms of physical movement,
cognitive abilities.
I asked him, how can we define mental health?
And his answer was very straightforward and very powerful.
He said, what we all need to aspire to is to be in states,
that is in the verb actions of agency and gratitude
for as much of our waking life as possible.
Now that sounds great, right?
A sense of agency, the ability to exert influence
over our internal state and affect the world around us
in positive ways, positive relationships,
reach our goals, as well as gratitude,
being grateful for the opportunities
that we've been afforded, even grateful perhaps
for some of the challenges that we've been afforded
or that were selected for us
that we had no control over
and carrying that agency and gratitude forward
because it gives rise to a sense of peace,
contentment and delight.
So all of that sounds wonderful, right?
Be in agency and gratitude as a verb states,
experience peace, contentment and delight.
But Dr. Conti acknowledged,
and we spent a good amount of time discussing the fact
that doesn't happen just because we decide we want to.
In fact, agency and gratitude,
peace, contentment and delight,
guys are up from a whole set of other processes
that we have to engage in on a regular basis.
And that really gets us back to those three drives.
He talked about how people tend to have
more or less aggressive drive,
not just aggression in terms of violence,
although some people do have that,
but in terms of their determination
and their sort of leaning into friction,
even seeking out a friction.
People are on a continuum
with respect to the aggressive drive.
He also talked about the pleasure drive
and the fact that people are on a continuum
of the desire for pleasure to either be a hedonist
or somebody who really avoids pleasure
and kind of restricts pleasure from oneself.
And again, that these things can slide around
depending on our life circumstances, our age, et cetera,
but that it's very important that we have a sense
of where we are on that continuum of an aggressive drive
and a pleasure drive.
And here's the most important thing,
that our aggressive drive and pleasure drive
never outsize our generative drive.
And that engaging our generative drive
is really the hallmark of mental health
that leads to that sense of agency and gratitude,
peace, contentment and delight.
And he defined the generative drive in the following way.
He said, the generative drive is our desire to create,
build and contribute to the world in meaningful ways
and appreciate the process to get there.
It is the core feature of our mental health.
So if you want to learn more about the various drives
and how they interact and how to access
more generative drive, again, that's all contained
in the four episode series with Dr. Conti,
but taking us back to the tools and takeaways
from that four episode series,
the process of journaling in free association mode
or the process of journaling in a conscious structured way
is really about trying to access the generative drive
and to build up that generative drive.
And one of the key things about conscious journaling
is that it affords us the opportunity
in a way that's not going to be seen by anybody else
to really think about what our goals and aspirations are.
Now you might say, you know,
I can't even think about my goals and aspirations.
I don't know what I want.
Well, that's fine.
Then you should journal about that.
However, most people have some sense of what they would like,
but most people are simply not comfortable
with writing those things out or even thinking about them.
And if you reflect on that, how could it ever be
that you would achieve those goals and aspirations
if you're not even feeling comfortable enough
to think about them or write about them?
And so the process of thinking about
and writing about your goals and aspirations
is perhaps one of the key first steps
towards being able to actualize those goals and aspirations.
And for some people, this might be very easy to do.
You can simply write down, say,
I want to be married by this age,
and I want to make X amount of money,
and I want to live here or there.
And certainly those sorts of goals and aspirations
are perfectly valid for this type of exercise,
but so are the sorts of goals and aspirations
that relate to feeling states.
Like, yeah, I would like to feel part of a community.
I would like to feel like an active contributor
to a community.
And then the essential thing is to really flesh out
the detail around those goals and aspirations.
You know, what size community?
Where do you see yourself fitting into this community?
Are you doing this alongside other people or by yourself?
In other words, to really get comfortable thinking
about what your goals and aspirations are,
again, completely from the perspective of self
and that you are going to be the only person
to see this particular document.
Now, I will be the first to admit
that the exercise that I just described,
not the free association journaling,
but the structured journaling of goals and aspirations,
I and many people find to be difficult to initiate.
Difficult to initiate because there seems to be
a bit of internal anxiety and friction around doing it.
There seems to be something that keeps many, not all,
but many people from feeling as if they are even allowed
to think about their goals and aspirations
because many people default to, well, then, you know,
I'll just be disappointed because it's not going to work out.
I don't want to think about what I want
because then I'll just be more disappointed.
And that particular frame of mind was actually discussed
in the series with Dr. Conti.
And he convinced me, and he's the expert,
that the opposite is actually true.
When we are able to overcome some of our anxiety
and really think about in a dedicated way
what we would like to create for ourselves in our lives,
both present and future,
and keeping in mind our events of past
because we always carry that life narrative forward,
then we are in a far better place
to actualize those goals and aspirations.
And he explained a variety of reasons why that's the case
in his clinical observations
and some of the other observations
that really support that statement.
So I highly encourage you to think about embracing
a process of journaling.
Again, you don't have to do this every day.
The journaling and the dream analysis
take a little bit more time,
but they are oh so valuable
for better understanding oneself concept.
And they really thread forward into real everyday actions
that can positively enrich your mood and mental health.
Now, any description of science-based tools
for mood and mental health would be incomplete
without including some tools related to processing of traumas.
Now, the processing of traumas is something that,
especially in the case of major traumas or repeated traumas,
really should be carried out
in concert with a expert-trained clinician.
That is a psychologist or psychiatrist
who's trained in helping people work through traumas.
However, even if you're working with somebody
who's expert in processing trauma,
there are specific tools that you can use on your own
to accelerate that process.
And for people who are working through
what are sometimes called more minor traumas,
these are sometimes called big T, big traumas,
and little T, little traumas.
However, that nomenclature doesn't take into account
the fact that most of us can probably tell
what the big traumas are for ourselves and for others,
but sometimes it's hard to tell
whether or not those small traumas,
the little T traumas, actually are big T traumas.
So this is one of the major reasons
why working with a licensed professional
is really going to be advantageous
and in many cases necessary to work through trauma.
That said, the self-directed protocols
for working through trauma
have a lot to do with how we think about,
but more importantly at times,
how we talk about those traumas.
And Dr. Paul Conte talked about this,
not so much in the four episode series with us,
but in a particular podcast episode
that he did with Dr. Peter Attia,
who some of you are perhaps familiar with
for his incredible podcast, The Drive,
but also for his excellent book, Outlive,
which deals with health span and lifespan or longevity.
Now, in that particular conversation
with Dr. Conte and Dr. Attia,
Dr. Conte emphasized the fact that one of the ways
that we hold ourselves back
and indeed can exacerbate the negative consequences of trauma
are the ways in which we modify our language
to describe those traumas.
And what he said, which is so important,
is that oftentimes we don't allow ourselves
to use language that's as big as is necessary
to explain that trauma and the impact of that trauma
on us and on others.
In fact, many people start to relegate their language
to more passable in a given sentence
or passable in a given conversation.
Now, what we're not talking about here is the idea that,
okay, you know, screaming at somebody else about your trauma
or using a lot of four-letter words
is necessarily the best way
to process that trauma verbally.
However, we are talking about allowing oneself,
either in spoken form or in written form,
to really allow the magnitude of a given trauma
to be expressed with a fair degree of intensity
and language that can capture at least some
of what that trauma represented for us or for others.
Now, as Dr. Conte pointed out,
all too often we do the opposite.
What ends up happening is people will experience
some sort of trauma, either major or minor,
maybe single or repeated trauma,
and rather than being comfortable talking about it,
rather than using language that captures at least some
of the magnitude of that trauma for them,
people start to talk about that trauma less frequently.
They start to distract themselves
to think about other things instead of talking about
or thinking about that trauma.
And what happens is that trauma roots
into our unconscious mind
and starts to impact us in negative ways.
Now, those negative ways include increases in anxiety,
disruptions in sleep.
In fact, one of the common ways in which trauma manifests
in disruptions in sleep by way of rooting
into our unconscious is that people wake up at 2.30
or three o'clock in the morning,
let's just say after several hours of being asleep,
and immediately they're thinking about that thing
that happened and they're upset about it.
The idea is that when we push those traumas down,
when we don't talk about them with people that we trust,
when we don't have a way to consciously process
those traumas using language that at least partially matches
the magnitude of the impact of those traumas for us,
well, then those traumas impact our unconscious mind
in ways that lead our unconscious mind
to literally wake us up in the middle of the night
and remind us of that thing.
It's as if it's being thrown back in our face
over and over.
Also, sometimes traumas will root their way down
into our unconscious and then they will resurface
in the mode of compulsive or obsessive thinking
about that thing or perhaps other things.
Again, the unconscious mind has a interesting
and complicated number of different ways
that it defends us in ways that it can create denial,
distraction, that we might get hyper-focused on work
as a way to not think about the trauma
or hyper-focused on some details in our environment
and just really trying to focus on that
because it's much easier to process
and handle that than these traumas.
Again, the processing of trauma is a whole landscape
into itself that actually was beautifully described
in terms of how it arises within us
and how to process traumas in a really structured way
in a just fabulous book that was written by Dr. Conti
called The Invisible Epidemic,
How Trauma Works and How We Can Heal From It.
And in that book, Dr. Conti explains a number
of different ways that we can do self-directed work
as well as work with licensed professionals
to process traumas and help us move through those traumas
so that they are not negatively impacting us going forward.
So I really encourage anyone that's trying to process traumas
from the past and or present to check out Dr. Conti's book
because it's a spectacular resource.
But in terms of the tools related to processing trauma
that we're talking about right now,
I think this point about really making sure
that we allow ourselves to verbally process
and emotionally process that trauma
in a way that there's room for using language
that captures some of the magnitude of that trauma
and how it impacted us and others
is going to be very important
because otherwise what ends up happening
is that we tend to adopt feelings of guilt and shame
around those traumas simply by not talking about them,
by having them go inward.
And then they start to negatively impact
our unconscious mind and then our unconscious mind
tries to throw them up to the surface
for our conscious mind to recognize
by waking us up from sleep.
And in some cases, by leveraging those unhealthy defenses,
things like denial, things like the overindulgence
in alcohol, overindulgence of drugs,
ways to distract ourselves,
as well as projection and sublimation
and the other types of defenses
that Dr. Conti talked about in the four episode series.
Again, those defenses are not necessarily good or bad.
It depends on the circumstances.
The unconscious mind is not trying to harm us.
Your unconscious mind is part of you.
It is you.
But of course it is you acting in concert
with your conscious mind.
And so really the tools and protocols
from the four episode series with Dr. Conti
are aimed at helping you feel and access
more sense of agency and gratitude on a regular basis,
more peace, contentment and delight.
And doing so by touching into those different drives,
understanding what they are,
the aggressive drive, the pleasure drive,
and really making sure that your generative drive,
again, I love this description of the generative drive
so much so that I'm going to read it again,
because this is really what it means to be mentally healthy.
Again, the generative drive is our desire
to create, build and contribute to the world
in a meaningful way and appreciate the process to get there.
It is the core feature of our mental health.
So being able to access that generative drive
on a regular basis is really what this thing
that we call mental health is all about.
And the tools that I just described,
of course can be combined with in any number
of different ways with the tools that I described
gleaned largely from the episode
with Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett.
And so what you now have is a kit of tools and protocols
for improving mood and mental health,
some of which are grounded in that core six,
the first principles of self care
are always going to be getting your physiology right
so that your psychology can be right.
As well, of course, you want to emphasize tools
and protocols that build up your psychological processes
and concept of self.
That's what the tools from the Conti series
that we just described are all about.
And then the tools from the episode
with Dr. Lisa Feldman Barrett sort of bridge the two
because she talked about both the physiological
and the psychological tools that really represent ways
to enhance our mood and mental health.
And so by threading these three things together,
I believe it really arms us with the greatest degree
of optimism and capacity to take control of this thing
that we call our mood and emotions,
and to, of course, allow ourselves to feel
the negative things we need to feel,
but then process them in healthy ways
and to exist as much as is reasonably possible
in generally optimistic upbeat states
that allow us to engage our generative drive.
And although we covered a lot of tools during this episode,
again, I want to emphasize that the idea
isn't to necessarily do all of them all at once,
maybe just pick one or two and start to implement them
on a regular basis.
And by implementing those, there's no reason to think
that you would be significantly eating
into your other demands on your time,
because ultimately the whole purpose
of having elevated mood and mental health
is so that you can have better relationship to yourself
and better relationship to others
and to the world around you.
If you're learning from and or enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel.
That's a terrific, zero-cost way to support us.
In addition, please subscribe to the podcast
on both Spotify and Apple.
And on both Spotify and Apple,
you can leave us up to a five-star review.
Please check out the sponsors mentioned at the beginning
and throughout today's episode.
That's the best way to support this podcast.
If you have questions for me or comments about the podcast
or guests that you'd like me to consider hosting
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
please put those in the comment section on YouTube.
I do read all the comments.
Not so much on today's episode,
but on many previous episodes of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
we discussed supplements.
While supplements aren't necessary for everybody,
many people derive tremendous benefit from them
for things like enhancing sleep, hormone support, and focus.
To learn more about the supplements discussed
on the Huberman Lab Podcast,
you can go to Live Momentous, spelled O-U-S,
so that's livemomentous.com slash Huberman.
If you're not already following me on social media,
I am Huberman Lab on all social media platforms.
So that's Instagram, X, formerly known as Twitter,
Threads, LinkedIn, and Facebook.
And on all those platforms,
I discuss science and science-related tools,
some of which overlaps with the content
of the Huberman Lab Podcast,
but much of which is distinct from the content
on the Huberman Lab Podcast.
So again, it's Huberman Lab on all social media platforms.
If you haven't already subscribed
to the Huberman Lab Podcast
monthly Neural Network Newsletter,
the Neural Network Newsletter
is a completely zero-cost newsletter
that includes summaries of podcast episodes,
as well as toolkits.
Toolkits are brief PDFs that describe in bullet point form
tools for, for instance, enhancing sleep,
neuroplasticity, deliberate cold exposure,
deliberate heat exposure, fitness,
dopamine regulation, and much more.
To sign up for the Huberman Lab Podcast
Neural Network Newsletter,
simply go to hubermanlab.com, go to the menu tab,
scroll down to newsletter, and put in your email.
We do not share your email with anybody.
Thank you once again for joining me
for today's discussion, all about science-based tools
for enhancing mood and mental health.
And last, but certainly not least,
thank you for your interest in science.
["The Huberman Lab Podcast"]